hello and welcome to the innocence
channel
is there a way to talk about how we
perceive the world act in the world and
make sense of the world that also
explains how other organisms communities
and systems operate
right from ant colonies to
teams of work colleagues
today we have daniel friedman helping us
understand a conceptual framework called
active inference which may be able to do
just that
daniel has a fascinating academic
background in biology and genetics his
phd was studying ant behavior he
co-founded the active inference lab i
really hope you enjoy this conversation
and can see how sensing inner bodily
sensations or interception fits with
this active inference
please remember to subscribe to the
innosense channel for more information
about the role of your bodily sensations
and tips for using
bodily awareness to improve your
well-being
thank you okay so good morning daniel i
believe it's pretty early on
in your homeland yes
yes it's it is early in california
6am
or 7am
okay so
thanks ever so much for taking the time
to or making the time so early on to
join us on the inner sense channel um
we're here today to talk about a topic
called active inference
so please could you tell me a little bit
about your background and how you ended
up establishing
the active inference lab which is
something that i've really enjoyed
viewing it's an online participatory lab
that's communicating learning and
practicing applied active inference
well thanks for the
invitation and yes looking forward to
unpacking a lot of this and i'll just
begin with my path and how we all
together came to working in this active
inference lab
so i've been a student of
biology
and genetics always very curious about
how different living systems worked and
enacted in their environments
and i
went to graduate school
did a phd in biology and specifically
that was in behavioral ecology in ants
and so for five years in graduate school
i did field work in southern arizona in
the united states and also a lot of lab
work and computational work and all
those experiences are kind of embodied
in their own way
and help just show me some glimmers of
how many different methods and
approaches and perspectives there were
on just one question like how do ants
make decisions about how to regulate
their foraging behavior at the colony
level so that's kind of what i've been
interested in from a research
perspective and during that time i was
also learning more about different
frameworks for perception cognition and
action
and
there are many such frameworks but the
one that i started to learn more about
in around 2017 and 2018
was the free energy principle and active
inference
so
mm-hmm
there i'll just leave there before we go
to the next chapter yes
wow so i'm i'm just curious about ants
and um how you study them in the field
so literally you were out these weren't
ants that had been collected in a kind
of glass container these were in a
literal field were they
yes
they were in an actual open grassy field
and ant field work was awesome
the methods ranged from highly
improvised
and
basic like using toothpicks and spray
bottles of water and stop watches and
little flags and a lot of just
things that are available objects and
questions that people could ask in their
local neighborhood or in their backyard
counting ants crossing one direction or
another on the trail but then also there
was the liquid nitrogen and collecting
ants and labeling them and giving them
pharmacological treatments and then
collecting them and measuring different
aspects of their gene expression and all
that comes with that in terms of like
the molecular biology
and the computation so ants are awesome
to study and i hope that we can continue
to tie that in in this conversation
because although your
wall and some of your previous
discussions focus on the humant
sometimes i just think about things in
terms of the ants and the colony and um
i think that just shows how when we do
have integrative ways
to talk about perception cognition and
action
everybody will have their own systems
that they've studied and phenomena that
they've looked into
but there will also be like a higher
language that helps us connect the dots
across those different systems
okay
yeah and i think that word language as
you just said is um
sometimes it's uh key i think you had um
was it mark solms on your channel
a while back and he um said
this phrase i think it was a avoid who's
wanting to avoid getting into semantic
tangles
and i think that is so
such a you know i love that that phrase
stayed with me and it's so um
such a useful thing to remember when
trying to have these sorts of
discussions that as you said we can be
coming from different perspectives and
have different experiences and different
languages to describe what we think
is
a useful way to explain our existence
but one person's
choice of words might have a very
different
semantic uh
reasoning or understanding to someone
else's so um
yes let's proceed um one thing i wanted
to mention now that the theme tune for
the active inference lab is excellent
was there any particular reason why you
chose that theme tune was it did it
represent
the free energy principle or active
inference or
it's got some stochastic elements and
some
nuns
the theme song was a special request of
a friend of one of the co-founders of
the lab yvonne and uh
dimashvakov is the name of the musician
and
at least i did not provide even any
suggestions but when i hear it i
hear how there's a
a regimentation
and an orderliness
but also
an energetic feeling and a motivational
and maybe even an action-oriented
feeling to it so it always is exciting
when i hear it um let me return to the
story of the lab so
in uh 2019
i connected with the other
people who we would all together go on
to co-found the lab and that was alex
and yvonne
and we were very interested in applying
active inference to organizational
design especially to online teams and
organizations
they had a background in systems
engineering and systems thinking
i had a background in thinking about
complex systems like the ants and also
learning about active inference and
altogether we
knew that we had a lot of
learning and applying ahead of us
and so we thought how will we
rise or meet
this
unknown unknown and
only parts of it we were in a position
to see at that moment
how will we meet this large challenge of
applying active inference a framework
which is still undergoing conceptual
development just like all conceptual
frameworks are but also one that we
believe has a lot of possibilities for
application and so we thought we're not
in a position to be hiring people to be
in an academic lab
getting graduate students and the pace
on that would be slow even if that were
an affordance that we had an opportunity
for action and so we wanted to
take the spirit of open science
decentralized science
and just participatory sense making and
bring some of these threads together by
offering this co-creative space the
active inference lab where participants
from different backgrounds different
time zones different levels of
familiarity with active inference and
other topics can come together and be
learning communicating and applying
active inference
that's uh really nice to hear the
background to that and the kind of the
the spirit of it being so open and
open to people joining in and i would
encourage anyone who's interested after
they've heard what active insurance is
to to subscribe to your channel and you
always take time in the first of a
series of
digesting papers to kind of really slow
things down and to um
cover all the the different concepts
that you're going to talk about in a
particular series so let's start by just
um in a nutshell can you explain what is
active inference please
okay well the first thing that comes to
mind with a question about nutshells is
hamlet
who said i could be bounded in a
nutshell and count myself a king of
infinite space
so
active inference is
very austere in some ways because the
kernel of this nut
the action perception loop
is
very
pre-application let's say it's very
general and it needs a lot of meat to be
added and more to that skeleton
before there's something there to
simulate or use
even as a thinking tool so
the kernel of the nut is
very
simple
almost to the point of being
infuriatingly so
like language so that would be my zeroth
pass would
be
the nutshell
is its own
domain
and inside of it there's so much space
to be developing and there's so much
that will sprout out of it
but
yes good okay so the
infuriatingly simple um bits about
action and perception what is that so if
there's someone you've never never
spoken to before you meet them
um
in an elevator what would you say action
active inferences
okay so here's how
i would uh perhaps approach that
it's all in the title active inference
is about integrating action and
inference
and then if we go one level deeper
we're using inference
which is to say like cognition or in a
computer happens to be computation
we're using inference as a way of
integrating our models and perspectives
on
action
with cognitive processes that include
planning perception emotion memory
anticipation so we have this tremendous
diversity of sensory processes those
could be our
visual sense our olfactory sense our
enteroception proprioception so we have
many
inputs
to the system
and then there's also a diversity of
actions that different systems select
and those can be like the sort of
on-board action opportunities the
on-board affordances for bodily action
and also they can include extended
affordances like using a computer or
using a pencil so we have a lot of
inputs and then we have a lot of outputs
so a lot of sense coming in a lot of
actions coming out and then there's a
lot of things that happen in between in
what we call broadly cognition again
like some of those features or phenomena
i mentioned like planning anticipation
memory etc
now we could have bespoke
narrow theories
for each sensory modality for each
cognitive phenomena and for each action
affordance
and or
we might be interested in pursuing some
integrative ways to unify
our formal models and our informal
models of perception cognition in action
so i believe that is what active
inference offers and then we can go into
in a second how it differs from some
other frameworks but i believe what it
offers is a way to think about that
input space the cognitive space and the
output space as well as in the impact
which is kind of the fourth quadrant
there thinking about all of those
in a unified way which at the very least
we have to do for useful computational
modeling but also just for useful sense
making
okay
so it really unifies all of the
different
components of our being you'd say of our
how we experience ourselves
is that going too far
each will use the map to navigate the
territory
so if it's honest in how you say it then
amazing i hope so
how does it sorry i was just going to
say how does it differ then from you
know other more classical ways of
viewing how living organisms go about
their business of staying alive
awesome
question
i
hope or as we would say an active expect
and prefer that in the future
there will be a url that i can provide
where these will be listed and
enumerated and more referenced but just
off the cuff
how does active inference differ from
other
potentially integrative theories for
action perception and cognition whether
they be cybernetic or more system
specific like a human psychological
theory so
one key difference
between active inference and some
frameworks for
biological and computational behavior
like reinforcement learning
is that in active inference action
selection is accomplished by
always the joint consideration of
epistemic and pragmatic value
epistemic value means the value of
information or of learning and knowledge
like epistemology and pragmatic value is
like utility or reward
and so in reinforcement learning there's
an emphasis on the common currency of
pragmatics
reward value and then
it leaves a bit of this awkward or ad
hoc way that curiosity and intrinsic
motivation has to re-enter and be
translated or transmuted into this
common currency of pragmatics like a
curiosity bonus right we'll pay you a
little bit to go on an extra epistemic
foraging trip
in active inference though we can have a
common grounding between epistemic and
pragmatic value which enables
our simulations and our embodied systems
to rapidly make decisions that
in one moment are more exploratory and
in the next moment can be more
exploitative over multiple time scales
so
first point is it's a way that different
than reinforcement learning we can bring
epistemic and pragmatic value into a
common ground
the second
is
short and that's as mentioned earlier
that in contrast with essentially any
other framework although i'm open to
hearing what else people bring to the
table it integrates
very diverse and heterogeneous
perceptual cognitive and action features
in at least an inter-accommodating
framework and so very few other
theories or frameworks attempt to have
such a scope
for example there might be a model of
just memory or of just action selection
but then those are like different
modules that then have an ad hoc
connection and so active inference gives
a principled set of connections and then
the last point that i'll make in terms
of differentiation with active inference
versus many other theories is
with active inference we can be quite
explicit about where are we talking
about the map
and where are we talking about the
territory
and so the territory how things quote
really are and the map how we're
modeling it and so i think about a
linear regression
and if we did a linear regression
between height and weight and we found
that there was a positive or negative
correlation or however it may be
nobody would think well you're saying
that height and weight are a linear
regression because the linear regression
is just a map it's just a model of a
territory and so similarly with active
inference though many times people are
interested in how things quote really
are how the territory is and may even
use active inference to discuss as if
they are discovering how the territory
is we also have this opportunity to be
very clear about map making
and i think that is a tremendous value
because it helps us hold a space between
the observations that we're taking from
a system and the modeling that we're
doing while also leaving some of the
mystery and openness
okay some of the mystery and openness um
the use of you know words terrain and
map mate
making there i think um
will be useful later on when we dive
into some of the
concepts uh of
that are
used amongst your colleagues and peers
in the lab um especially when it comes
to this idea of
you know
um
sometimes it appears like the terrain
and the map are identical you know day
to day as i go about my daily life i
feel that what i
you know things happen so quickly that
it feels like um i'm actually that
the terrain and the map
equal each other but what i'm hearing
here saying here is that um
active inference
gives us an opportunity to understand
how
the map is formed and how it relates to
the changing terrain is that right
yes
so we're all
without falling into any
simple fallacies were all inside of our
sensorium
pick a different spatial metaphor if you
choose but we are not directly observing
lightning strikes in clouds we're
receiving sensory input in the form of
sound and light in that case of like
lightning and thunder and then we're
doing inference on a hidden cause an
unobserved cause again though we observe
the sensory consequences of the
territory and we can take a totally
action oriented realist pragmatic let's
get out of this open field because
there's a thunder and lightning storm
happening so we can make useful action
while also
holding that space and not thinking well
we won't be able to take useful action
until we're in that cloud directly
observing the lightning strike it's like
no we are observing the light and the
sound
and we're making an inference about
unobserved causes
and we can share that with each other
and we can decide how to act based upon
that
and then maybe when we're
hanging out in the house we could talk
about what is real and what lightning
really might be but there's also this
ability to be
applying active inference again at the
level of mapping
while also holding space for some
philosophical questions about the nature
of the territory
okay so
i think this is getting to a really key
point here so the sensorium um way i
understand it is that that's just that's
a way of describing the the collection
of different things we might sense so
it's our
a bit like um you know we have the
genome and the microbiome or collections
of genes and microbes but the sensorium
is our
global collection of sensors so not just
the five sensors as you said um
the uh
interception proprioception all of these
things um maybe ph blood pressure
temperature
uh
changes in air pressure outside of us is
anything that we might sense either
consciously or
subconsciously
yep
and if i could bring in one term from a
field that active inference draws a lot
on which is ecological psychology
um ecological psychology provided that
notion of affordance which is like a
capacity for action so it's something
that could be selected on the outbound
and then a sort of complement to the
term affordance is umvelt and yes it's a
german term or something like that and
i'm sure it could be looked up and
searched more but it is exactly
referring to that sensorium which is
that integrated
perceptual experience
and inactive inference that is actually
an actively generated
process and we can experience that
directly with our visual input so
in the anatomy of the eye
there's actually color
receptive cells
that are more concentrated in the center
of the eye so there's higher resolution
and there's color vision in the center
of the eye and that actually kind of
drops off in color perception and in uh
clarity
as it goes out and of course there's a
quite large blind spot in the eye which
is like where the optic nerve is coming
out
yet
our visual experience or at least a
possible visual experience has the
felt sense of color
in all parts of the visual field equal
clarity and quite curiously no blind
spot right
so even just in the visual modality
before we get to multi-sensory
integration or some of these more
ineffable senses we're already quite
aware that that umvelt that sensorium
is not just a signal processing it's not
just the microphone and then the filter
and then the central processing unit and
then the action selection unit there's
actually something quite dynamic where
even when we close our eyes we can still
continue to have a generative model
but when our eyes are open that too is a
generative model
one that is meeting
a compromise
with the incoming sensory information to
be sure
but also is actively generated by the
generative model of the organism
okay
so
um
just to sort of quote i think it's anil
seth from his book being you he's he
says that all of our perceptions are
controlled
hallucinations that
happen um with through because of you
know our body so
um
this so it's not just
visualizing things we visualize with our
eyes closed that are
kind of uh models
actually everything that we perceive
is
constructed as a kind of uh to help a
model to help us
understand things which are beyond our
direct ability to ability to
and to perceive directly
yes i think we can even explore this
notion of perception as active or
generative in two senses so the first is
in this sense of the generative model
for example a vision where there's this
um generated visual scene what anil seth
calls the controlled hallucination that
is being met with a compromise by
incoming sensory data and that can be
modeled using bayesian techniques but we
won't go down that road so that's one
sense that perception is generative and
active just to summarize is it's not
this passive receiving it's something
endogenous internal
and then being met with a compromise
with internal uh
incoming information and the other sense
that perception is quite importantly
active it's an amazing example that's
used in the recently
introduced active inference textbook and
i think it also speaks to this map
territory distinction and the importance
of action for perception and so the
experiment the embodied experiment goes
like this
place one's finger on their pants
and so
that is
i'm gonna do this now so on my thigh
just when you say pants in english sorry
in england means underpants but i can do
it on anywhere on my trousers
now i have reinterpreted many of my
previous awkward interactions now i'm
just kidding
yes on one's favorite piece of clothing
or fabric on the couch if they may
is the fabric rough
and the answer is actually to even
determine that
the finger must be moved
because the roughness is a is a feature
that we do active inference on
through
actual physical motion
and
by reducing our uncertainty through
action
we're integrating action and perception
and so we couldn't just
sit there so to speak with our finger
unmoving
and think about whether it's rough or
not so here the fabric is like the
territory and the map is how rough is it
there maybe there's parts where it's
rough and there's parts where it's
smooth
but how could we know if all we have is
a finger in a dark room
we need to move it and that actually has
a lot to do with other cases of active
perception like ocular motor
movement eye motion when we're reading
or scanning
or all other kinds of things that people
can think of where
the sensory inputs
are not predestined or determined but
they're actively sought after
in a way
that is more like seeking and informed
foraging rather than just
ad hoc sampling
that's a really
simple but powerful examples so i can't
tell if something's rough or smooth um
[Music]
i could guess it if i was looking at it
but by touch i have to move i have to
take this active part of the to infer
whether it's rough or smooth and
so that's a kind of an easy to grasp
physical example because um we all know
how to move our fingers
and feel texture um but what we're
saying is that
that principle
applies to all types of
inference um yeah it's act there's an
active component and i guess that makes
sense with sound because we can only
you know it's the moving between
pictures isn't it it's the change that
allows us to interpret sound if it was
all
just one tone and constant we would
never
be able to distinguish between anything
audible
and and just one other example so we've
mentioned the physical palpation with
touch and touch receptors and so it's a
yes and with all the biology of the
touch receptors so this is something
that is here to again be a yes and to
all the molecular biology of touch it's
just adding in this note that in the
organismal context action is part of the
perceptive process then we mentioned the
visual scanning and then a third example
might be in communication where somebody
might have uncertainty about whether
they're conversant
is
on the same page as them or seeing what
they're seeing or whether they're
grasping or comprehending so it's like
we already have these visual and tactile
and even prehensile or grasping
metaphors
for communication and cognition and we
might take an active step of like asking
how does that sound to you or what does
that make you think about or does that
make sense what we're planning here
those are an example of communication
as action and inference in the
interpersonal and that's an example
about how active inference can be
applied
at the cellular and at the organismal
level
but also at the interpersonal level
which again speaks to one of the
important aspects of this integrative
framework which is that it helps us
connect the dots with different systems
and skills
and um
that helps me appreciate the
the concept of an affordance as well
which you you mentioned
so
you can't really you know so an
affordance from what i understand is
that the quality of something so you
know a cup
um has got
grasp ability i can hold it but
to um you know to a fork laying on the
table that the
the cup isn't graspable because the fork
isn't
doesn't ever use cups
so it's that the fact that we have to
actively do something that makes the cup
have the affordance of being graspable
um
and an important piece there is that
relationality or the way that you
described how the affordance it's not
like we could just tag the cup as being
grabbable by whom
not even by all humans and so actually
the concept of an affordance and this
radically relational nature of
affordances and situational helps us
bring accessibility into the picture
bring personalization and just other
situational context because there's no
such thing as an affordance that is
agnostic to the actor
and so
again it's an example of a qualitative
insight
like interactions are relational or
preferences expectations affordances all
are conditional on the situation those
are quite qualitative
felt senses that many people may
resonate with
they might not have on their own
connected that to bayesian statistics
and formal models of the action
perception loop however
we're all increasingly finding that
indeed those connections are there and
hopefully we can hold the space for
there to be a continuum of discussion
again between those qualitative insights
like context matters
and some formal models for action and
perception in context
okay um
can we uh think about i'm looking at
your mission statement again for the
active inference lab so it's um a
participatory online lab that's
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference can um
we think about the practicing applied
part so
um
in what ways can active inference be
applied once you become aware of the
concept how can you
apply it
or practice it
awesome well i look forward to
a thousand applications blooming so i
have more uncertainty than certainty on
that question because i think we're just
beginning
a few areas where active inference has
been applied
if i could list them and then we can see
which ones might be interesting the
first is in the area of
bodily physiology whether in
terraception as well as in mental health
and in
cognitive dynamics so there's a lot of
work that's been done in a clinical and
in a psychological
domain
a second area is in the group
level so thinking about online teams and
communities as we and others have and
modeling group communication as a case
of active inference and then the third
might be in robotics and embodied
non-biological systems or systems that
we want to imbue with some natural
perceptive cognitive and active features
but are not
the same type of biological thing as we
are so those would be three quite
interesting areas would be the
organismal and bodily the community team
group communication space
and the embodied robotics
i find that the so uh the second one the
hardest to to kind of see how that be
applied i can see how you know in as you
said mental health and um
uh
yeah in the health domain it's it's
really easy to apply or possible to
apply and also
robotics or artificial intelligence
because
you know it's all very much about being
able to
take action and infer and all of that
but for the the group dynamics um
now can you give a sort of example about
how the concept of active inference
applies in a group setting
i'm thinking about your ants in the
field now
yes yes is the ant the nest mate or is
the ant the colony well aren't colonies
just sets of nest mates
but aren't nest mates just sets of
organs and aren't organs just sets of
cells and so on and
how do we think about collective action
and
again
somebody may have no issue with thinking
about an organism as being the locus of
perception cognition and action people
make decisions right
yet
groups also make decisions sometimes
explicitly like through what is quite
literally called policy decision making
in governance or in an organization we
also call that policy selection in
active inference so sometimes groups
make
overt policy selection and there's some
type of internal process
of determining that like a vote or
however it's done
so just as we could think about the
subunits whether they're modeled or
unmodeled in the organism
leading to an organismal decision about
policy we could also think about an
analogous process
be it implicitly or explicitly reached
for how groups are making decisions
and then that is that interesting
question where well i mean
again groups don't have perceptions
cognitions and actions they're just
composed of people who do okay fine but
then people don't right it's just the
cells and that's the um reductionist
slippery slope
and then one can also um
take the train in the other direction
the holist slippery slope well
individuals be they cells or organisms
or groups they're always in an
ecological context and so they actually
can only be said to be
a bit player in their decision making
because they're part of these extended
enacted networks of action
and so it's like we know there's a train
that slides us down the reductionist
path and we know there's a train that
slides us down the holism path and so
much work beyond active inference has
observed that relationship or tension or
dialectic and again active inference is
like maybe in that metaphor like the
train conductor helping us do something
useful and move things back and forth
and have fun and hang out on the train
while we're in a qualified way and
hopefully in a principled and rigorous
and accessible way
modeling these different scales of the
system
yeah the uh policy and politics and
group decision making that makes sense
now it's reminding me of a conversation
i had with um
professor of politics called laura cram
from edinburgh university so her day job
is to
um is academic and to look at uh
uh politics and decision decision making
within politics but um outside of that
she teaches she's a yoga teacher and um
has created a
uh
a type of yoda called interception yoga
or that's what she brands it as um and
she cited a very
interesting study where it was looking
at um decision making in politics and
you know um
as the person as a person enters a room
into a meeting
uh depending on what the
what flags are placed in front of them
that they see from different countries
will influence
the decisions they make
in the meeting so
you know it's uh
the
this idea of the symbolism
of what's presented in front of us
influencing the actions we take the
decisions or the actions we take and
that's just from a flag you know and
so
fascinating stuff mind-boggling stuff
that makes me think about
pauling or pulling when
there's an assessment of sentiment for
example within an organization or within
a country that is kind of like
interception at that group level
there's the the palpation that's like
the customs are on the border on the
interface
and then there's the enteroception which
is like the sensing within
and so as i've listened to your work and
seeing this area of interoception
develop
it reminds me of sometimes that
external focus
that perception cognition and action
have had
and
now i think we're seeing new ways of
balancing
not prioritizing or ranking they're just
different
complementary processes of x tarot and
enteroception
and wouldn't it would be awesome to have
unifying ways
of talking about them and modeling them
so this didn't have to be like
this topping of food versus this topping
or like sports teams
there are not team exteriorception and
team interception there's
the organismal mystery
and the
territory then there's how we model it
our mapping and sense making process
which is participatory and collaborative
and built on the shoulders of giants and
so on and so to be able to again respect
but also
have usefulness in that space brings us
back to active inferences focus on both
the epistemic and the pragmatic value
and how in moment to moment those shift
you're doing something useful and then
all of a sudden you need to go do an
action that's useful because it helps
you reveal something an epistemic action
and so just again having fluidity to
talk about those two sides of the
enteroception exteroception coin and the
two sides of the coin with epistemic and
pragmatic
two sides of the coin with perception
action it's kind of this minimum of two
idea that pervades a lot of the
discussion that gives us flexibility but
also the ability to like drill in and do
useful things
fascinating
uh do you daniel do you have any
personal
experiences or examples to share of how
uh viewing the world through the lens of
active inference has
influenced your own life changed your
behavior or
um
allowed you to see
things differently or situations
differently than you did before
if you can remember life before active
inference
when i was a young forager
well
there's probably many
expressible and ineffable ways to
address that and i
think of it as a show not cell but the
example that comes to mind is again
related to my ant research as i was just
beginning to study this area so on one
hand i was reading and learning not
doing anything useful
from the point of view of perhaps some
but i was learning because i was
continually being surrounded by novelty
and new information and what was very
exciting and just meeting my curiosity
with this endless stream of papers and
formalisms and then on the other hand i
was there in the field with the
stopwatch and the ants and so i thought
how can there be a synthesis
of the ways that the ants research
community has modeled the multi-scale
system that are the ants
and this kind of abstracts notions that
i'm learning in active inference
and i acted i reached out to authors and
i started sketching different models and
that
moved on to a path
that resulted for example in 2021
in an active infra-ants model
and so that was something where it
wasn't on my radar
when i started that process of action
and curiosity in tandem and so i think
that active inference
through bigger longer time scale
phenomena like just described like
adjusting one's research agenda or
regime of attention as we might say
towards applying active inference
to a phenomena that i was already
interested in but then seeing how that
plays at a much shorter time scale too
it's just fun to weave together the
concepts and find the patterns across
different systems and phenomena
yeah i got a sense of the the looping
there so you went from
curiosity to
action reaching out to people and that's
that loop has kind of snowballed i
suppose and brought you where you are
today
wonderful
so i first became of aware of the term
active inference after
reading it in a paper by seth and
tristan on the topic which this channel
is all about which is interception and
the paper was called active
interceptive inference so they they
jammed intraceptive
in between uh active in inference and
the emotional brain and it um so it
speaks to the heart of innocence channel
and
the way i understand it is that um what
we what we can see is a model where
signals from our body so these
feelings that we um
sense from inside our body
can be used to
update our
predictions about the state of the body
so you know
i'm now hungry because my stomach's
rumbling for example
or um
and we could just leave it there or we
could actually lead to an action that
helps us return to helps to keep stay
alive basically um return to homeostasis
so this is
you know my
um uh
blood vessels dilate or contract and
that helps me
move towards food for example
so we
carry on like if i can give it on the
temperature example and how active
inference deals with homeostasis that
return to a normal temperature range or
ph or blood sugar range
but also how active inference deals with
allostasis which is sometimes where
stress is actively pursued by an
organism or they make a decision that's
anticipatory like choosing to bring a
jacket with the expectation that it will
be colder outside so
in those kinds of settings which we
interpret as cognitive like if a robot
or an ant did it we would think that it
was thinking because it planned
to bring the jacket along and so that's
like allostasis or planning because it's
the expectation through time of body
temperature and actions can be taken in
anticipation about future expectations
somebody can wince before there's a
physical impact and there's probably so
many other
examples so just wanted to add that
point that a lot of frameworks deal with
homeostasis and the return to like a
control region and that's very familiar
to the areas like cybernetics and
control theory
but where are those frameworks without
this deep generative model concept
sometimes fall a little short
is in dealing with situations where
there's uncertainty about the future but
actions are taken now
to ameliorate that uncertainty about the
future or to bring
body temperature into alignment again in
the future but not putting on the jacket
in the house but preparing a future
affordance you just want to bring that
up because that temperature example it's
both a basic example used in cybernetics
and control theory and homeostasis and
physiology but just by moving into that
example again qualitatively before we
layer on any math or any variables we
can think about the reality of how
temperature is modulated in the world
and that opens up a very rich discussion
about other cognitive features that
would be really important to consider
yeah thank you um yeah the term aloe
stasis um
is uh less well-known than homeostasis
and um
as you're saying that so you know
um lisa feldman barrett has come up with
the term body budgeting which as i
understand it is equivalent to
allostasis and it's so it's got that
kind of idea of budgeting or forecasting
as you say planning into the future and
the body bit is about that it's looking
after our
you know our energy or resource budget
or balance um
so the unless you as you use that
example of temperature and putting on a
jumper i was thinking okay that's that's
for me personally
and then i might build a house to
control my temperature environment for
my family and then we have
weather broadcasters and weather
stations which if you're going back to
your point about group um decision
making you know if uh
the weatherman or woman says tomorrow
there's gonna be a snowstorm then that
changes the decision that has an act
people will take action on a kind of
city or country or nation wide scale so
um would you say that's
allostatic control at a group level or
active inference at a national level
absolutely the weather person provides
a high and a low temperature let's just
say but another way that they could
share those two temperatures would be
like the midpoint and then the variance
around that midpoint and so that's still
sharing two numbers so instead of saying
it's going to be between 20 and 30 we
could say it's going to be like 25
plausibly plus or minus 5 and it still
could be outside with a smaller
probability but 95 or 99 of the time so
absolutely what they're conveying is
their
estimate and uncertainty
which is kind of like where epistemic
humility comes into play we say things
like i'm not sure about or i'm quite
sure about and again that's reflected in
that weather report is it 28 to 32
or is it 10 to 40. so what is the
variance and we always hold space for
that mean estimate and the variance
estimate and yes the weather report
is being utilized as an actionable
signal for people who then take actions
from their set of affordances based upon
the information they're receiving so
then people go and buy a jacket if they
hear that there's going to be an
upcoming string of cold days for example
and
so yes it's a great example about how
communication
at the group level
is happening through information
technology
and through meteorology but then also
there's that biological version of like
different cells and different organs
kind of like sending weather reports
and um
there was a professor at my graduate
school craig heller who made this
awesome and interesting technology it
was like a glove and there was other
variants that had a slight negative
pressure
and then it had cool but not cold water
circulating and it turned out that that
was able to
reduce the body's temperature and that
previously many um approaches that
people had taking to recovering people
from hypothermic or hyperthermic
entailed
putting cold or hot appropriately on
like their thermal sensors
and that actually sometimes suppressed
the body's actual thermal response
because it's like the body's overheated
and the danger is the core overheating
but then the thermo sensors
like on the shoulders would become
cooled down so the person would
immediately feel relief
but it shut down their endogenous
vasodilation actual heat dissipation
which created a dangerous situation and
so this is like a way of
not using active inference but of course
could be modeled as such and working
with the ways that bodily and group
systems actually do communicate and make
decisions
rather than thinking that we can just
intervene in this one specific way
i love that example and
it
sort of reminds me of some of the
therapeutic approaches for dealing with
something like anxiety or phobias
where you're wanting to you know stop
the overall system from um
going about its you know it's normal
action perception loop and
find an entry point and give it a
different way to update its its model or
update its action
um so that it doesn't turn into a
vicious cycle um
and you know that that method i suppose
which they had a negative pleasure glove
or something you said i guess that's
similar to some of these techniques like
um
you know the wim hof method or something
where the the person is
training themselves so that their body
doesn't um
i guess you could say that the set
points the uh
allostatic set points are being shifted
by the practice or
the
the model of how dangerous the world is
is being changed um by the practice so
the the perception of threat is being
altered
yes
entities are taking actions
that are aligned with the kind of entity
they expect and prefer themselves to be
and that's something that for sure can
be unpacked and explored but perhaps
methods of training like the breathing
methods that you mentioned
in a sense they update i'm the kind of
thing
that is chill in a cold shower
that's me i'm that person who does take
a cold shower who has the discipline to
do so and who sees that being enacted
not the kind of entity who observes the
book being unread on the table about
cold showers but doesn't feel the cold
i'm the person who is now perceiving
taking deep breaths and all that comes
along with that from the vegas etc
while i'm also getting that cold water
and that is where the updating and the
development happens
not in the hypothesized experience so i
think there's some amazing and deep and
relatively lesser explored territory
with how we
frame
our own interception and development
and um i mean we i'm tempted to sort of
go deep in this on the and go into the
free energy principle and
um
uh
expecting ourselves to be in a state and
but i'll save that maybe for another
time um
i am aware we're coming up to an hour
and this was um due to being our
hour-long meeting um
do you
i wanted to go into some of the terms um
that you use with your your colleagues
uh but i think we'll maybe we'll leave
that um
can you if i could give a closing note
there just yeah on a historical and a
relatively closing issue then we can
however much shortly longer you'd like
several years ago and in earlier
developmental stages of this framework
there was i would say less clarity
between what the free energy principle
was and active inference
and so i hope that increasingly it
becomes distinguished
and that people can find accessible
on-ramps onto both but for those who are
listening this far in yes it would be
awesome to unpack it in the future but
active inference is about that action
perception loop and free energy sort of
meets there and goes in a totally
different direction
well i don't know if it's totally
different but it is a different approach
and so like it is a different way that
we can go
okay so yeah if anyone watching or
listening to this is curious about the
free energy principle then there's lots
to be
enjoyed on that topic
um
one one question before we wind up do
you have any thoughts about
when
uh
interceptive active inference could
become
maladaptive
to an organism
as i am only an ant doctor i can only
speak to that
but it makes me think about
anteroception and i think well how could
it become maladaptive in the colony
if its
internal perception for example of how
much food it has
becomes maladaptive what if it's
continuing to forage and just store up
seeds
way beyond what's reasonable what if
there aren't enough seeds but it isn't
foraging because it's not elicited to do
so because it's colony level and
terraception isn't happening or what if
it's blocking up its entryway every time
it gets cloudy
and that's actually like a false
positive rate that's unacceptable but it
would be appropriate to act that way
sometimes when it does flood in the
desert but it's not that way every day
and so i think it's a very interesting
and important area to understand how
different
contexts and different people in
different cognitive systems find
themselves in situations where
the ball rolls downhill and it all makes
sense yet it goes in a way that we don't
prefer and so again it both does make
sense why the body and mind and spirit
are compensating in a given way but also
we may want to
be part of that process and move it to a
different space
yeah so those two examples are really
you know nice examples
uh about gathering resources like food
you know do i need to keep hoarding
hoarding hoarding hoarding or not or
that's fine to let the cupboards go go
empty we'll be fine
everything's okay
and the weather one you know the oh it's
a little bit cloudy batting down the
hatches for the next month
uh but nothing actually happened
or the other other extreme
don't believe the weatherman and then
i'm sure there's analogies at the
organismal and at the social level
well thank you so much
for your time and i've really enjoyed
this conversation
where can people well what's on the
horizon for the active inference lab
over the next few weeks and where can
people find out more about your work
awesome yes thanks again and i look
forward to continuing the interaction in
different ways
so to learn more about academic lab head
over to activeinference.org
and you'll find a lot of resources there
you can also find our videos and other
content and so on as well as find out
about your affordances for participating
in the lab so that's definitely the best
way to find out more some of our next
steps just to name a few include
discussions with none other than you
where we'll be with some other authors
of work on osteopathy in the therapeutic
alliance and a lot of other fascinating
topics and we continue to develop some
educational materials as well as work
through the textbook there's a lot of
learning and applying that people are
involved in inactive lab
great exciting times
and awesome yeah really fun times i've
again i'm looking forward to continuing
it and
one hour is not enough but one year is
not enough so onwards we forage
onwards we storage thank you so much
daniel
thank you see you later bye